Register of the I͡U. Kruzenshtern-Peteret͡s papers
Hoover Institution Archives
I͡U. Kruzenshtern-Peteret͡s papers
1923-1983
2001C26
Hoover Institution Archives
6 microfilm reels (0.9 linear feet)
Memoirs, correspondence, writings, printed matter, and photographs relating to Russian literature and Russian émigré affairs.
Kruzenshtern-Peteret͡s, I͡U.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Location of Originals
Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biographical Note
IU. V. Kruzenshtern was born in Russia on June 19, 1903. Her father, a military officer, was transferred to Harbin when she was three years old, and in her memoirs she describes her life in this city. After her father volunteered for service at the front in 1915 (where he was killed), she and her mother moved to Vladikavkaz.
Following the Revolution, Kruzenshtern returned to Harbin, where she worked as a correspondent for various Russian periodicals. In 1930, she moved to Shanghai, continuing to work as a journalist for Shankhaiskaia zaria and The North China Daily News. There she married the poet Nikolai Peterets, who died young of tuberculosis.
Evacuating to Brazil following the Communist takeover in China, in 1960 she arrived in the United States, where she found employment as a commentator for the Voice of America. Following her retirement, she continued to work as a journalist for Russian newspapers, and even edited the San Francisco daily Russkaia zhizn'. A book of short stories, Ulybka psishi, was published in 1969. Kruzenshtern-Peterets died on June 8, 1983.
Scope and Content Note
Iustina V. Kruzenshtern-Peterets (1903-1983) was a poet, writer, and journalist in China and the United States. She wrote for a number of émigré publications, among them Gun-Bao in Harbin and Vecherniaia zaria in Shanghai, and Novoe russkoe slovo and Russkaia zhizn' in the United States, and also worked as a commentator for Radio Liberty (the collection contains transcripts she worked on; see SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/General/Transcripts). Of particular interest is her correspondence with well-known émigré writers and poets, and her untitled memoirs of life in Harbin and Shanghai (SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/Untitled memoirs and "V krasnom Shankhae," Russkaia zhizn', 1961). The collection later passed through the hands of Mariia Tourkoff (Vizi), and includes explanatory notes in her hand, as well as photographs and certain additional material in the subject file.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Russian literature.; Russians--China.; Russians--United States.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1934-1958 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Book written by Kruzenshtern-Peterets's husband, and programs, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Book by Nikolai Peterets (husband), entitled Mladorosskoe stanovlenie, printed copy, 1934 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Programs of theatrical evenings involving Kruzenshtern-Peterets or her plays (Box-folder 1: 2)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1932-1983 (Boxes 1-2)
  Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - General
    - General, 1970-1983, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Sodruzhestvo, 1966 (Box-folder 1: 4)
      This book includes inserted letters and cards from the authors of the poetry published within, and a review of the work.
  - Unidentified, 1932-1970 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Akimov, N., 1972 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Altenkirch, O., 1965 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Anderson, Larisa, 1957-1977 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Antonova, Elena, 1962 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Arensburger, Konstantin, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Avtonomov, Nikolai Pavlovich, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Baikalov-Latyshev, Sergei, 1969-1979 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Balakshin, Petr P., 1959 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Baranova, N., 1968-1970 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Bibinov, M. S., undated (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Cheremshanskii, Iurii Apollonovich, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    Includes third-party correspondence.
  - Daniels, Guy, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Fedorov, P., 1974 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Filipov, Boris, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Foster, Liudmila, 1969, undated (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Frank, Evelina, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Ginchas (Ginkh), Nikolai Sergeevich, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Goldstein, Michael, 1972 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Golembiovskii, E., 1972 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Ivannikova, Lidiia, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Klenovskii, Dmitrii, 1958-1970 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Kormilev, N. A., 1982 (Box-folder 1: 27)
    Includes third party correspondence.
  - Kovalevskii, Petr Evgrafovich, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Kudashev, N. V., 1976 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Lavrova, Nina, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Lukashkin, Anatolii Stepanovich, 1979 (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Magerovskii, Lev Florianovich, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - Medi, N. P., 1962-1971 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - Mendousse, Ivan Petrovich, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Naumenko, Viacheslav Grigor'evich, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - Odoevtseva, Irina, 1957-1972, undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Includes attached poetry.
  - Ore, Anna, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Pereleshin, Valerii [See: Salatko-Petrishche, Valerii F.]
  - Rais, Emmanuel, 1970 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Remizov, A., 1957 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Rokitiansky, N., 1982 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Rozhkovskaia, A., 1973 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Saburova, Irina, 1969-1977 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Salatko-Petrishche, Valerii (literary pseudonym Valerii Pereleshin), 1970-1981 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    General note
    See also: SUBJECT FILE for writings by and other information on Salatko-Petrishche.
  - Shatalov, Vladimir, 1970 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Shtein, E., 1975 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Sovremennik, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    Includes letters from E. Bobrova and V. Savin.
  - Struve, Gleb, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Sukhanin, Pavel, 1965 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Sumbatova, E., 1971-1977 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Szenfeld, Ignacy, 1972 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Tauber (Staroff), Ekaterina, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 2: 16)
    Includes letter to M. Tourkoff.
  - Veidle, Vladimir, 1970 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Vozrozhdenie, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Zalesskii, Mikhail Nikolaevich, 1958 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Zelenskii, Evgenii, 1975 (Box-folder 2: 20)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1958-1982 (Boxes 2-4)
  Articles, books, letters to the editor, plays, poetry, transcripts, short stories, and memoirs, arranged chronologically by title.
  - General
    - Fragments, undated (Box-folder 2: 21-22)
      Holograph and typescript
    - Letters to the editor, 1969-1982, undated (Box-folder 2: 23)
      Typescript and printed copies. Includes associated correspondence and polemics with other readers.
    - Newspaper columns, 1967-1981, undated (Box-folder 2: 24)
      Printed copies. Contains only brief pieces. Longer, serialized articles are listed by title below.
    - Poetry, undated
      Typescript and printed copies
      - Original (Box-folder 2: 25)
      - Translations (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Transcripts of Radio Liberty broadcasts, undated (Box-folder 3: 2)
      Typescript
    - Untitled short stories, undated (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - "Adam the Mameluke,", undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - "Brodiachaia sobaka,", undated (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - "The Drama of a Mailman,", undated (Box-folder 3: 6)
    Typescript. Includes untitled Russian original.
  - "Eshche ob odnom paskvile,", undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - "Kiev,", undated (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - "Lastochka,", undated (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - "Legenda o Dalai-Lame,", undated (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - "Loshadinaia zala,", undated (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - "Ma Sy-Tsun i Mei Lan'-Fan,", undated (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - "O poezii, o russkom iazyke i fal'sifikatakh,", undated (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - "Pervyi i poslednii,", undated (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - "Poema o prozaicheskikh liudiakh,", undated (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - "The Recipe of Happiness,", undated (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - "Runy Brailia,", undated (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - "The Seventh Aunt of Dr. Shen,", undated (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - "The Song of Freedom,", undated (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - "Tolstoi po Truaia [Troyat] i podlinnyi Tolstoi,", undated (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Untitled article about foreign medical educational establishments in Shanghai, China, undated (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - Untitled memoirs, undated (Box-folder 3: 22-23)
    Typescript. Some sections/chapters are fragmented.
  - Untitled memoirs, undated (Box-folder 4: 1-3)
  - Untitled play, undated (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Untitled article about Lermontov, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - "Velikaia liubov': Pamiati A. V. Belinkova," Vozrozhdenie, undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
    Printed copy
  - "Milye shutki,", 1958(?) (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - "Moia plemiannitsa Teddi," Russkaia zhizn', 1960 October 18 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - "Kar'era zabludshei ovtsy," Russkaia zhizn', 1960 October 25 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    Printed copy. Includes typed English translation entitled, "The Career of a Stranded Sheep."
  - "V krasnom Shankhae," Russkaia zhizn', 1961 August 22 - September 26 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - "'Iskhod' russkikh iz Kitaia," Russkaia mysl', 1968 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Ulybka psishi, 1969 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - "Mozhno li zhit' bez shipiashchikh,", 1972 March 5 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - "Sud i sovest': Pamiati S. Kucherova," Novoe russkoe slovo, 1973 March 25 (Box-folder 4: 14)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Put' soldata," Russkaia zhizn', 1975 May 2 - June 20 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - "Korabl'-prizrak," Russkaia zhizn', [1976] (Box-folder 4: 16)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1934-1981 (Boxes 4-5)
  Brochures, clippings, leaflets, poetry, typescripts, and correspondence, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Cossacks (Box-folder 4: 17)
    Includes information on the Leib-gvardii Kazach'ego Ego Velichestva regiment as well as on atamans Grigorii Semenov and Boris Annenkov, General Ivan Pavlichenko, and others.
  - Dissidents, Soviet (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Kuramoto Incident (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Marxism (Box-folder 4: 20)
    Typescript by Boris Filipov entitled "Iz zabytogo i zamolchannogo," undated.
  - Mitropol'skii, Arsenii Ivanovich (literary pseudonym - Arsenii Nesmelov) (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - Poetry, Russian (Box-folder 5: 1)
    Collected poetry (holograph, typescript, and printed), most of it unattributed, as well as reviews and biographical information on various poets.
  - Romanoff family (Box-folder 5: 2)
    Includes information on M. Goleniewski, pretender to the throne.
  - Russia--History, 1917-1921 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Russians--China (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Russians--Foreign countries (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Salatko-Petrishche, Valerii Frantsevich (Box-folder 5: 6)
    Includes his writings as well as biographical information about him.
  - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr Isaevich (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Miscellany (Box-folder 5: 8-9)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1966-1981 (Box-folder 6: 1-5)
  Issues of various émigré periodicals, such as Chasovoi, Russkaia mysl', Voennaia byl' and Zarubezhnaia Rus', as well as clippings from American periodicals on general topics.
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1923-1977 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  Thirty-four prints of various people and places, mostly from Harbin in the 1920s, and apparently primarily acquaintances of Mariia Tourkoff (Vizi), rather than Kruzenshtern-Peterets.